Guide to the Playing Card and Game Collection 1549-present (Bulk 1800-1899) PR 115
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Playing Card and Game Collection
1549-present (Bulk 1800-1899)
PR 115
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
16.0 Linear feet (17 boxes)
The collection includes American and European playing cards and card games, primarily from the 19th century. Includes one of the oldest dated cards in existence.
Provenance
The majority of the collection was acquired in 1937 as part of the Elie Nadelman Folk Art Collection. However, no clear records exist as to which decks were part of that accession. The collection also contains materials from other donors and from purchases.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to 20 photocopies per day per person. Suitability of the original for photocopying is at the discretion of the staff. Neither blueprints nor tracings can be copied under any circumstances. Duplication of large-format items will be done by the house photographer. See Print Room guidelines for details.
Historical Note
The origin of the playing card is difficult to pin down to a specific time or place. Playing cards are known to have existed in China before 1000, and probably spread west through trade routes. Playing cards were found in the Middle East by the 13th century, and in Southern Europe by 1350. Cards moved north from France into England by 1459. Playing cards were initially hand-painted, which contributed to their use among the noble classes of Europe. With the development of the woodblock method of printing, ca. 1380, mass production of cards was possible, and card playing became a widespread leisure activity. As printing processes developed throughout the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries, cards were printed in greater detail, in color, and more inexpensively.
Suits found on Islamic cards were cups, coins, swords, and sticks. These were reinvented in various ways by different countries and cultures throughout Europe. The Spanish suits are similar: cups, coins, swords, and clubs. Italians used the same suits, but feature the king seated. The suit signs in common usage today are the French system: hearts, diamonds, clubs, and spades (hearts, trefoils, squares, and spearheads to the French). Hearts, acorns, bells, and leaves are German suit signs. Swiss suits are acorns, shields, bells, and roses. This collection contains examples of all of these suit variations. Each nationality has developed differing ways of rendering the court cards.
The earliest known playing card with a date written on it is from 1546. This card is part of a deck in this collection. French cards from before the Revolution in 1789 show full-card depictions of Kings, Queens, and Jacks. When the Monarchy fell, kings and queens were no longer popular, and the figures were de-crowned and became representative of democratic ideas like liberty and equality. The monarchs were re-installed on cards at the time of Napoleon's reign. There are many examples of pre-Revolutionary French cards in this collection.
The nineteenth century was a time for much standardization, and at the same time, experimentation on the part of card manufactures. American card manufacturing began in the early 1800s; previously, decks had been imported from England and taxed. Transformation cards, where the suit signs are incorporated into comic or sentimental pictures, began to be printed at the beginning of the 19th century. Corner indices, or the practice of putting the suit sign and number in the corner of the card, took off in the second half of the nineteenth century. After 1860, most cards began to be standardized with numbers. The Joker card first appeared in American decks of euchre around 1865. Most playing cards had plain backs until the 19th century, when designs were added. Advertising material began to appear on card backs in late 19th century, first in Belgium. Souvenir packs with different photographic views on each card were introduced in the 1890s.
"Standard" decks are considered to be those able to be used by the average card player. This most often results in 52 cards (13 each of 4 suits) and 2 joker cards. "Non-standard" decks are often used to play specific games. Bezique, a game in the collection, has 64 cards. Other non-standard cards are used for educational purposes and for games of memory and chance. Transformation cards are also considered non-standard.
Cards have often been used for fortune telling. Many are identified as "Le Normand Style" after a deck named for Napoleon's personal fortune teller. These cards contain a small image of a playing card in the upper center of each card, with a number above. The remainder of the card has a fortune image. Tarot was a game invented in Italy, although tarot cards are today used for fortune telling. Political messages are often found on card decks. In many cases, both in Europe and America, political card decks were issued close on the heels of the depicted event.
Games played with playing cards make up a significant part of this collection. The small size and portability of playing cards made them useful to game designers. Often a small folding board would be included with the deck of game cards. Dissected puzzles, or metamorphosis games, were popular. In these games, different cards are components of a whole picture (heads, torso, and legs, for example) and were to be interchanged or else matched to their corresponding parts. The rebus, or picture puzzle, was another popular game printed on playing cards. These cards would show a picture, and sometimes a written clue, and the game was to guess the answer. Rebus cards have been produced since 1789.
Playing card wrappers are also notable ephemera because cards were one of the early products sold in packaging. Decks of cards were thus one of the first pre-packaged manufactured items. Early cards decks were packaged in paper wrappers held together with a piece of thread. Cardboard slipcases were in use by 1800, boxes with push on lids by 1828, and telescope and tuck-flap boxes were introduced in the late 19th century. Cellophane wrappers were common by 1937. Original containers have been retained with the card decks in this collection, and are sometimes boxed separately.
General note
Bibliography
Galt, David. "The Romance of American Playing Cards," New England Antiques Journal, Vol. XVII, No. 8, February 1999.
Greenwald, David. "In One Era and Out the Other," Games, Jan/Feb 1981, p. 14.
Scope and Content Note
The Playing Card and Game Collection spans the period from 1546 to the present, and contains over 200 decks of playing and educational cards, as well as playing card-based board games and other game materials. The collection is divided into five series: American Playing Cards; British Playing Cards; German and Austrian Playing Cards; French Playing Cards; and Other Playing Cards. Decks are organized by date within these series.
Printing formats represented in the collection include: woodcut, engraving, lithography, chromolithography, and photomechanical printing. The cards in this collection represent several types of decks: standard, political, educational, transformation (in which the suit marks are incorporated into an unrelated design) and translucent (which reveal hidden scenes when held to the light.) Fortune-telling and tarot cards appear in the collection, as do metamorphosis cards and games.
The cards cover a wide range of American and European styles. 149 card decks are of European origin and 60 are American. Many European cards are multilingual. Eleven board games meant to be used with playing cards are included in the collection. A device for keeping score and counting the number of games played is also in the collection.
In 1983, game designer and collector David Greenwald (now Galt) was hired by the New-York Historical Society to catalog the Society's collection of cards and card games. Much of the information about each deck comes from his work, which resulted in individual catalog sheets for each card deck and an exhibition at the Society. When the collection was processed and re-housed in 2000, the cards were organized into series based on country of origin, and numbered by date within each series. Mr. Galt's meticulous research as to the suit signs and numbers of cards of each deck can be viewed in the collection database.
Arrangement
The Playing Card Collection is organized into series based on country of origin.
Series I. American Playing Cards (1824-1983)
Series II. British Playing Cards ([1675-1887])
Series III. German and Austrian Playing Cards (1549-1884)
Series IV. French Playing Cards ([1668-1901])
Series V. Other Playing Cards (1699-2000)
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
Playing cards can also be found in the Bella C. Landauer Collection of Advertising and Business Ephemera (PR 031).
A.D.F. Randolph & Co.; McLoughlin Bros., inc.; Murphy Varnish (Newark, N.J.); Nadelman, Elie, 1882-1946–collector; Parker Brothers, inc.; Tiffany & Company; U.S. Playing Card Co.; W. and S. B. Ives (Firm); Bezique; Card games–Equipment and supplies; Chromolithographs; Divination cards; Educational games–Equipment and supplies; Engravings; Erotica; Lithographs; Playing cards; Playing cards--Czechoslovakia; Playing cards–Austria; Playing cards–England; Playing cards–France; Playing cards–Germany; Playing cards–Spain; Playing cards–United States; Puzzles; Rebuses; Tarot cards; Woodcut
- Series I. American Playing Cards (1824- )
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I spans the period from 1824 onward. The decks were originally organized by date, with undated decks first, and alphabetically within each year. Decks range from standard and souvenir to those depicting historical figures, or issued for charades. Those added after the collections arrangement in 2002 have been given consecutive numbers.
  Notable cards include the rare "M.V. Card," or the Murphy Varnish transformation and promotional pack from 1883. The "Union Playing Cards" from 1862 are also rare and are notable for the patriotic suit signs: eagles, stars, shields and flags. Kings and Jacks in this deck are representations of Union colonels and Queens are depicted as Liberty. The "Norwood 85" pack is also rare, although it was published by the U.S. Playing Card Co, a commercial card publisher. The pack was issued in 1900 in honor of the new millenium and U.S. Playing Card Co.'s new factory in Norwood, Ohio. Shortly after issue, the entire printing was withdrawn, probably due to the potentially risque back design of Cupid and Psyche in embrace. Few other known copies of this deck exist. The "Game of Poke" is a deck of cards hand drawn in an American mining camp.
  Other cards in this series include charade cards and political cards. "PIT-Bull and Bear Edition" is a commodities exchange game in which different commodities appear on each card. "Votes for Women" was issued by the National Woman Suffrage Publishing Co., Inc. of New York in 1919. The four Spanish American War decks (billed as a "Game of factual questions") are part of a larger "Starry Flag Series." A "Mexican American War" deck includes generals of that war shown as Kings. "Columbian Exposition" cards each show an exposition building. This series also includes game counters for keeping track of card games and "Salesman's samples" from The New York Consolidated Card Co. in New York; one each of many kinds of cards for sale.
  Creators of decks in this series include W. and S.B. Ives of Salem, Mass.; the United States Playing Card Company; McLoughlin Bros.; Anson D.F. Randolph of New York; Chas. E.Carryl for Tiffany & Co.; A. Dougherty for Murphy & Co. Varnish Makers; and Parker Brothers, Inc. of Salem, Mass.
  - Faro Cards, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - [Game Counters], undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Grandmama's Geographical Game, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - [Roodles Card], undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Lafayette, 1824 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Improved and Illustrated Game of Dr. Busby, 1843 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Improved and Illustrated Game of Dr. Busby, [1843] (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Game of Kings, [1844] (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Master Rodbury and his Pupils, [1844] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - The Game of Kings, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - the New-World, a Game of American History, by a Yankee, [1845] (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The Errand Boy -- or -- Jack at all Trades, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Guessing Game, [1846] (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - [Poke Cards from an American Mining Camp], [1846] (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - [Mexican-American War], [1849] (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - [Thomas Crehore], [1850] (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - American Chronological Cards, or Uncle Thomas' Game for the Young Patriots of America, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Calkin's Games at Words, with Letter Cards, 1859 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Game of the Rebellion, 1861 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Union Playing Cards, [1862] (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - The Game of Bezique Complete (with separately boxed container), [1865] (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - [L.I. Cohen], [1865] (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - [Samuel Hart & Co.], [1865] (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - [Rebus riddles], [1870] (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - [American Manufacture], [1871] (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - [Mauger], [1873] (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - World Making and Taking; Wie die Arbeit so der Lohn, 1877 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Harlequin Playing Cards (with separately boxed container), 1879 (Box 3, Folder 28-30)
  - Gaigel Playing Cards for Export NO. 3, 1881 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - The M.V. Card, 1883 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Hard-a-Port, [1890] (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Hard-a-Port, [1891] (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Columbian Exposition, 1893 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Game of Familiar Quotations from Popular Authors, [1893] (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Monarch [bicycle], [1895] (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - The Stage Playing Cards #65X, [1896] (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - In Dixie-Land, 1897 (Box 4, Folder 38.1)
  - Southern California Edition Souvenir Playing Cards, [1898] (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Lee at Havana, 1899 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Schley at Santiago Bay, 1899 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Schafter at Santiago, 1899 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - War or American Soldiery and Battles, 1899 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Dewey at Manila, [1899] (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Game of Phillipines. Facts, Faces, and Figures, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Game of American Battles, [1900] (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Norwood 85, [1900] (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - No. 48 Pinochle Playing Cards, [1900] (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Sample, [1900] (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - PIT -- Bull and Bear Edition, 1904 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Souvenir Playing Cards of New York City, [1911] (Box 5, Folder 51-52)
  - Movie Souvenir Playing Cards, 1916 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Votes for Women, 1916 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Ye Witches Fortune Cards No. 62X, 1917 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - No. 47 Circus Playing Cards, 1919 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Americards -- America's Newest Game for Adults, Youths and Juniors, [1941] (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - [Happy New Year, Merry Xmas], 1947 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - The Best of Country Music, [1978] (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - The Best of Country Music, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Iran-Contra Scandal Playing Cards, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 60.1)
  - Presidential Playing Cards - Hillary, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Presidential Playing Cards - Rudy, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Respect Iraqui and Afghan Culture Cards (issued for U.S. Military Personnel deployed in Iraq and Afghanistan), 2007 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Respect Iraqui and Afghan Culture Cards, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Presidential Playing Cards - McCain and Palin, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Presidential Playing Card - Obama, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee (JDC) Cards, 2008 (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Tiffany & Co. Playing Cards, [1960] (Box 17, Folder 68)
  - Kem Playing Cards, [1960] (Box 17, Folder 69)
  - Delta Airlines Playing Cards, 1979 (Box 17, Folder 70)
  - National Airlines Playing Cards, [1970] (Box 17, Folder 71)
  - TWA (Trans World Airlines) Playing Cards, [1965] (Box 17, Folder 72)
  - Space Dominoes, 2000 (Box 17, Folder 73)
  - Space Dominoes, 2014 (Box 17, Folder 74)
  - Obaminoes, 2011 (Box 17, Folder 75)
  - Instructions for Obaminoes (Box ., Folder 75A)
  - Southern Pacific Railway Playing Cards (partial deck), n.d. (Box 17, Folder 76)
  - Pioneers of Photography Playing Cards, 2016 (Box 17, Folder 77)
- Series II. British Playing Cards
  Series II. dates from 1675 to 1887. The series includes 24 card games, of which many are geographical and educational card decks.
  "The Pretended Popish Plot" deck was issued in 1679 to rebut the fears of British citizens that a Catholic conspiracy was attempting to unseat Charles II. "Counties of England and Wales" is a very rare deck, few other complete packs are known. "Game of General Knowledge" includes 5 small decks with different genres of factual questions on each.
  This series also contains "Click tablets," wooden boards with printed cards pasted on to the board's face. The board tablets are attached with ribbon and can move in a variety of ways.
  Cards are ordered by date and thereunder alphabetically by name or subject. Cards with known dates always come before those with circa dates.
  - [Click Tablets], undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - The Cries of London, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    General note
    See: Box 15
  - [Domino-style Geographic "Playing Cards"], undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Counties of England and Wales, [1675] (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - The Pretended "Popish Plot" of 1678, 1679 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Wallis's New Geographical Game Exhibiting a Tour Through Europe, 1794 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - The Game of Pastora or the Shephardess of the Pyrenees, 1796 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - The Geography of England and Wales, 1799 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Walker's tour through England and Wales. A New Pastime, 1809 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Geographical Game of the World (container only), [1810] (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - The Welcome Intruder into the Social Circle (with separately boxed container), [1815] (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Metastasio (Metastasis), [1816] (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - History Made Easy; or, A Geneological Chart of the Kings and Queens of England, 1817 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - [Roman History], [1825] (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Wallis's New Geographical Game Exhibiting a Tour Through England & Wales, [1825] (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Royal Playing Cards, 1827 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Court Game of Astronomy, [1827] (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - New Geographical Cards, 1828 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Court Game of Astronomy, [1828] (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Historical Pastime: A New Game of the History of England from William 1st to William 4th, 1831 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Historical Amusement [with separately boxed rule booklet], [1840] (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Snap Bumble (Oliver Twist Series): A Favorite & Popular Round Game, [1863] (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - [Goodall & Son's Purple Pack], [1865] (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - The Game of General Knowledge, 1887 (Box 7, Folder 24)
- Series III. German and Austrian Playing Cards
  Series III. contains 62 decks, with date ranges from 1566 to 1890, and 2004. This series holds many notable decks, as well as the oldest dated playing card. "Stukeley's" cards, after those in the British Museum" contains 13 cards out of an original deck of 48 or 52. Some of the cards, dated 1546 on the 9 of hearts, have worm holes. This may be the earliest surviving date on cut cards (A date of 1544 appears on an uncut sheet of cards). The accompanying wrapper tells of the 1797 discovery in a country barn of the cards "contemporaneous with Martin Luther." These cards closely resemble cards in the British Museum, which are known as "Stukeley's Cards" after their discoverer.
  "Biedermeier" and "[Translucent Deck]" reveal erotic scenes when held to the light. "Jeanne d'Arc," from 1805, is the oldest of all published transformation card packs. The images are derived from Schiller's play "Joan of Arc."
  "Metamorphosen der Neuzeit fur Knaben" (Modern Transformations for Boys) includes interchangeable heads and bodies. The resulting people can stand up like paper dolls. "Frag und Antwort Karten-speil" (Question and Answer Card Game) is another metamorphosis game which doubles as a conversation game: the top section contains a question and the bottom sections contain interchangeable answers. "Musicalisches Kartenspiel besichend in Kuhreihen" (Musical card-game consisting of round-singing) shows lines of Thuringian folk-songs on each card, one song per suit. "Spielkarten vom Jahre 1848" depicts the events of the 1848 Austrian revolution.
  "Das Delphische-Orakel" (The Oracle of Delphi) offers at least six different kinds of games which could be played with just one deck. A fortune telling game, sentence-formation game, dice game, lottery game, word-formation game, and checkers-type game can all be played with these cards, which feature multiple scenes and numbers on each face.
  Cards in this series were manufactured in Vienna, Frankfurt, Leipzig, Göbl, Tübingen, Linz, Augsburg, Nuremberg, Berlin, Munuch, Neub, and Darmstadt, Germany. See the database for more detailed information on creators and publishers. Cards are ordered by date and thereunder alphabetically by name or subject. Cards with known dates always come before those with circa dates.
  - Das Delphische-Orackel oder neueste Zauber-Karten, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Dolls House Deck, undated (Box 7, Folder 2-3)
  - [Fortune Telling Querant], undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - [Mini-metamorphosis], undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Praeziosa's Orakelsprache Zweite Lieferung, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Wahrsagekarten, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - [Wust], undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - ["Stukeley's" cards, after those in the British Museum], 1546 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    See: Box 16
  - Bauern Hochzeit, 1780 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - [Matchbox of Metamorphosis], [1800] (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Jeanne d'Arc, 1805 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - "Wallenstein", 1807 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - [Multi-themed court pack], 1810 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Karten Almanack, 1815 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - [Eurich's Tarock], 1817 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - [Tarock (pre-Cego?)], [1820] (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Naturgemählde, [1825] (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Plastische Naturgeschichte des Thierreiches, [1825] (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Wer's Kleine nicht ehrt JST's grosserre nicht werth, oder Wenn's nicht regnet so tropfelt, [1825] (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Das Brautpaar mit seinem gefolge im Kreuzdomino, [1828] (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Das Uhr - und Stundenspiel; Le Jeu d'horloge et des heures, [1830] (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Der Maskenball/Le Bal Masque, [1830] (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Der Peruckenkonig, Ein unterhaltendes Gesellschaftssspiel, [1830] (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - [Four Continent German Cards] (with separately boxed container), [1830] (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Frag und Antwort Karten Spielen in 24 Komischen/weiblichen Figuren, [1830] (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Jeden Lappen gefallt seine Kappen, [1830] (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - [Street Cries], 1835 (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - The Game of Nations or what country do I belong to?, [1835] (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Musicalisches Kartenspiel besichend in Kuh, [1840] (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Auction neues Wurfelspiel/Encherere amusant jeu aved dès, [1845] (Box 9, Folder 31)
  - Fünfzig deutsche Bilder Räthsel, hieroglyphen Calembours und rebus (for instructions, see Box 15), [1845] (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - Spielkarten vom Jahre 1848 (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - 20 Deutsche Wortespiele, [1850] (Box 9, Folder 34)
  - Der Kampf um die Braut; Le Combat pour la Fiancée, [1850] (Box 9, Folder 35)
  - Deutschland's Barometer/The Barometer of Germany (with separately boxed counters), [1850] (Box 9, Folder 36)
  - Kleine Tanzer-Metamorphosen; The little metamorphoses of dancers, [1850] (Box 9, Folder 37)